hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and I'm here with a special report
before the regular program starts the
program has been produced for a few days
and in fact has been up on the web for a
day already but I wanted to get this out
to you as quickly as possible so I'm
tagging this on to the beginning I went
out to pick up some food tonight and
when I was waiting for it to be made
there was a little flyer that was on the
counter from epic drugstore which is a
chain of drug stores I believe it's a
national chain I know it's owned by
JCPenney and since JCPenney is a
national department store I'm assuming
that Eckerd is a national chain of drug
stores as well so I'm paging through
this flyer and I see a laser pointer on
sale for 7.99 now as you may remember a
few weeks ago one of the whole talk
listener Steve Michael came on the show
and he told us about his work producing
laser Holograms using a laser pointer a
49 laser pointer that he picked up at
Edmond scientific he sent me two of the
Holograms a laser transmission hologram
and a reflection hologram and they were
beautiful
so I was going to go down to Edmonds
tomorrow which is Monday and pick up one
of these 49 laser pointers until I had a
chance to see this ad now this 7.99
laser pointer is called the bullet beam
laser pointer it's manufactured by a
company called Vector manufacturing and
it is five milliwatts it is 650
nanometers and in wavelength and it runs
on three Ln 44 1.5 volt batteries
which totals out at about 4.5 or exactly
4.5 actually now here's what here's the
exciting part of this a lot of people
think that you should get as close to
the wavelength of the helium neon laser
as possible to do Holograms but actually
without the materials if you ever look
at their specification sheet and the
response curve the actual materials are
actually more sensitive to the deeper
red part of the spectrum than they are
the part of the spectrum that the laser
helium neon laser produces
so not
not necessary to be close to 633
nanometers what you need is the
coherence length of the diode itself
now apparently this diode that Steve
Michael bought has a lot of coherence to
it because he's produced very deep
Holograms now whether this one does or
not I don't know but I'm going to find
out I actually bought two of them one
I'm going to run off the batteries and
the other one I'm going to run off of a
Radio Shack power supply here which I
notice I do have a 4.5 volt setting on
it so that I will never have to buy
batteries again I just run it off of
house current
and I'll tell you what if I find out
that I'm doing a hologram with the 7.99
laser pointer I am just going to be
jumping up and down three o'clock in the
morning I'll tell you it's going to be
absolutely fantastic there's quite a bit
of excitement about laser pointer
holography ever since that news broke on
holotalk a couple weeks ago and it's
fantastic why go out and spend 800 for a
laser when you can get one right now I'm
holding in my hand for 7.99 it's just
going to revolutionize holography in
this country not at the upper end of the
research end obviously but at the end
where you've got your amateur and
hobbyists and people who have always
wanted to do Holograms but never had the
resources to go out and spend 800 or or
so for a laser and a Optics and all this
other kind of stuff so in any case this
is my report for the week I'm going to
go into the lab and start experimenting
with this laser diode and I will come
back on next week and let you know what
the report is if I do not have any luck
with it I'm going to run down to Edmonds
pick up the same one that Steve Michael
has which operates I believe he said
it's operating at 640 nanometers but I
don't think the wavelength should have
anything to do with it the active
materials actually Peak
at around 710 to 720 as I sit here and
look at the graph the curve and the 633
it begins to rise in sensitivity from
that point until it reaches its peak
right after the 700 nanometers so if
you've got a 670 nanometer laser diode
even though it's dimmer to the eye than
the 633 it still received better by the
emotion on agfa materials you've got
less of an exposure time because it's
more sensitive to that part of the
spectrum
so here's this week's show at Rob Taylor
is the guest he's from fourth
dimensional holographics and I'll be
back next week with a report take care
[Music]
the following is the production of
Frankie Freitas and the internet review
of holography
hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to holotalk for the week of
December 7th 1998. my guest this week is
Rob Taylor owner of fourth dimension
holographics in Nashville Indiana Rob
will be filling this in on what's hot
this holiday season with Holograms along
with a few new directions is gallery and
Retail shop will be taken such as his
new holographic portrait Services
next week I am going to replay the Steve
Michael interview due to several
requests one of which is the publication
holography news which is going to
publish the announcement of the program
running so this will give their
subscribers an opportunity to log on and
listen as you may remember Steve is
creating Holograms using its standard
out of the box laser pointer and I have
to tell you the excitement about this
has not yet died down at all
I'm going to be taking some time for the
holidays and family so Hollow talk will
be off the air with new programs until
we pick it up again for the week of
January 10th which will then take us all
the way through to Memorial Day at the
end of May
so what I'm going to do is go through
this season's archives which aren't yet
available on the archive page and grab a
few shows maybe from the beginning of
this season in September and rerun them
over the holidays
so let's move on to the Rob Taylor
interview as usual I'm not going to come
back on after the interview so I will
thank you now for tuning in
also I'd like to wish all holotalk
listeners a happy holiday season from
our house to yours and hope that it is
filled with the love of friends and
family
hello to my daughter Faith who is away
at College as a physics major
Dawn who is in the Marines and getting
ready for intelligence training
looking forward to having you both home
in two weeks
so daughter Renee who helped me around
the studio which I really appreciate
since it's just as much time working
resources to do this show as it is any
weekly radio broadcast
of course my wife Debbie and we're
coming up on 25 years baby love you all
okay folks here's the bobtail interview
I'm out of here
you should really start off by you
telling us a little about the gallery
that you have in Nashville Indiana how
it got started where it was and where it
is now yeah
we opened up our little Holo shop about
eight years ago and uh 800 square foot
area uh a commercial space in Nashville
Indiana and Nashville is kind of unique
because that most of Indiana is
relatively flat you know farmland
where we're located is kind of in the
heart of the Hoosier National Forest in
Southern Indiana and Nashville has the
largest state park in Indiana and so
we're in a small rural
Community but we also have a very big
tourist-based economy and there's a lot
of shops and crafts people and things
and town we get maybe two or three
million people through Grand
County that Nashville is located in a
year so it works out well and we decided
to put a hologram Gallery shop in and
it's worked out real well
we had the like I said we opened it up
about eight years ago about six years
ago we uh actually uh put a studio in
the back of our shop and we had a
four by eight foot hand table in the
spectrophysics 125 laser TV on laser
which we're doing some production of
mastering and uh silver halide work but
just this summer we closed both the
older studio and the
up and move to a 1700 square foot space
wow got a good opportunity to move into
it so we've expanded and uh it's worked
out real well now we haven't opened up
our new studio yet but the
Museum and the gallery and the shop are
all open and it's working out real nice
of course a lot more space and
before we were always kind of cramped
and we've got more room and we can play
some real nice Holograms some more
aesthetically it's
what made you decide to get involved
with retail holography out of all the
things that you've chosen anything too
about
back in
12 years ago I lived in Dallas Texas and
I had a carpet cleaning company and we
were doing real well in Dallas and I
sold that carpet cleaning company and uh
I have a wife and two children they were
real young at the time
you know when you have two kids your
priorities start to change and I wanted
to get back to my native state where I
was born and
raised my kids in a in a small rural
community like I was raised and so we
decided to move back and I was looking
for something to do and I'd always been
interested in the Legacy I majored in
Fine Arts photography and you know
college and so holography had always
been a fascination of mine so when we
were about ready to leave we happened to
come upon a gallery in Dallas and they
still are there I believe it's called at
least an image yes and
that was really the what gave me the
impetus to start the shop in Nashville
so we went ahead and just went ahead and
opened up our shop and I guess you could
say the rest of the system now you're
not just involved with selling holograms
on the wall from what I understand
you're actually a dealer with some of
the newer holographic recording
materials as well is that right yeah
um just uh July of this year we were
given the opportunity to become a U.S
Distributors distributor of the slavish
holographic materials that are made in
Russia
that was really exciting for us because
with the the minds of the AG phone
materials we really believe that the
slavich material is going to be the
material that takes eventually takes the
eye of axis uh place and we think they
make a really good holographic material
and uh so yeah since July we've been a
U.S distributor for them and
that we we're also Distributors of about
six six different manufacturers of
display holographs besides our own stock
image line we've had we represent about
six different manufacturers so yeah
we're real excited about that too are
you working with the slavage materials
now
um currently no we don't have our studio
open when and we closed our studio when
we moved to our new space so we're not
using any of it right now
when we open our new studio next year uh
spring or early summer of next year will
be definitely using the Salvage material
that's going to also be a
holographic portrait studio right yes
yep we're real excited about that also
it's uh it seems like everything's
coming at the same time but I've been
working for a long time I've always been
interested in pulse photography and
watching the technology develop as we've
been in the holography industry and uh
there's a company in Lithuania called
giola yeah that makes a
post laser camera system and
January of this year I went to visit
them in Lithuania and we've actually
trained on the camera system and
actually helped them put together the
finishing cosmetic touches and some of
the final Optical arrays and the camera
system of the first prototype
that they have for sale and it's really
really interesting for me not just only
the trip itself but being able to go
over there and experience it because
they're really on The Cutting Edge of
the post photography they're using the
new neodymium
Yelp technology stuff for Imaging it's
really a really good
green wavelength of laser like to work
and that basically just sits on a
desktop too doesn't it no it's a it's on
an optical table itself it's probably
about three by six foot I would guess is
the optical table okay
um it's a
the laser itself is a two Jewel laser
and then you have outside the actual
camera sticking itself there's the you
know uh various mirrors and that mounted
the tripods to give you your pathway for
your both your mastering and your
talking nodes
what materials do you hope to shoot
these holograms on the slavage yeah
we'll be using exclusively slavish
material when we get that camera system
you can live just because we're
Distributors there's really not a lot of
choice anymore for as far as was at the
commotion I mean there's the German
material and there's a China material
but other than that there's not really
much in to choose from
I was on your website which is a great
site you have a shot on there that I'd
love which is a two-channel animated
shot of you in the studio doing an
exposure I love that that was the old
Studio
what would some of the listeners find
when they go to your website why don't
you let the listeners know what what all
you have there
uh on the website itself yeah well
basically list all our different
Services
um you know it tells about our gallery
and our retail store
um kind of list some of the Holograms to
the top 25 programs that we sell there
we also have a website a web page that
to the uh our Slavic distribution site
so that people can find out about the
different
technical specifications then we also
are kind of uh advertising or premiering
their photography studio that we are
going to
experience but those are basically the
different categories that we're trying
to advertise in our web I put that web
page I designed the web page earlier
this year and then actually a
High School senior from the local school
actually did the code writing and
everything
yeah they did
now can people order Holograms from you
retail Holograms
we take orders over the phone and
through the internet all the time we
ship if not every day probably every
other day and especially right this time
of the year you know it seems like this
is our
here as far as the retail store a lot of
people buy holograms for gifts for
people that they can't figure out what
else to get them what is hot for
holography this year as far as display
holder
oh okay well
um what's moving the Jesus stereogram if
there's uh that's always been a hot
seller especially right around Christmas
time and the Star Trek series both the
old Prismatic Star Trek series and the
light tricks uh Star Trek series those
are always been good sellers
um there's
uh The Matrix make a really good line of
photopolymer holograms they're really
bright and efficient Holograms and they
do do quite a few different ones and
they're all real good sellers like their
emergency prey prey of a three-channel
hologram of a hawk and an eagle and an
owl that's a good seller uh they'd be
one of the Dracula the braumstick or
Dracula and also a three-channel showing
three different transformations of the
page uh generally
any hologram most of the Holograms that
we sell would be within the 40 to 100
range I would say yeah
also uh Derek Galen up in Canada has a
new line of holograms called red star
elegant and
he he hasn't been moving real well like
he'd have an alien and uh
a beer bottle a Heineken beer bottle
now he's producing these up there I
believe you yeah that's Royal
holographic anyway yeah
do you have any fine artwork there from
any of the holographic artists
when I've got a lot of tall telegrams
from Ron and Bernadette Olsen they do
some really really
to my knowledge the only other
neodymium-based
based Health technology for holography
here in the United States is that the
series that was produced by Hughes
uh well those were done on photopolymers
with the Hues as you probably know
they're gone
in the holographic end of it so most of
those are have been sold I have a few
photopoliters left but not very many of
those those were really good sellers
because because they were on
photopolymer that you could reduce the
cost of them and they were sold real
well unfortunately there's just not a
lot of people to be able to produce one
photo polymer anymore and so uh Ron and
Bernadette are all on glass plates right
now okay either using slavage glass
plates or the acts of melon mask plate
that's used for
photolithography that's interesting
we've got some pieces that we've just
got on loan from other people uh that we
have to sell that we just put in there
except for the kind of like our little
mini Museum that we have here yeah we've
got
a large laboratory microscope that was
done by olaton and that was given to US
Bank uh holocan have
a
portrait of Ronald Reagan and we had the
portrait that portrait was done by
olicon cosmopage uh that one I believe
is the only U.S president ever been
recorded I think Jeffrey Murray was
actually doing copies for that yeah I
think he was I think he had a few for
sale I don't know
still selling age or not but that was a
really lucky thing for us to get because
you know the value of those will just
continue to go up yeah now do you own
that whole room
[Music]
yeah that's down in the National Gallery
yeah yeah
and we've also got uh some truthful
color Holograms done by Con Chicago
[Music]
some of the experimental plates that
were just that
different subject matter where
independent plate and three different
lasers and being able to record static
objects that were the continuous waste
but ninja real life we actually sell
some of those templates
well for anyone he may be in the area of
where your shop is located why don't you
give some information as far as your
hours of operation and different things
like that for the holiday season oh okay
sure
um well we're generally open from uh 10
until 5 during the week and then on the
weekend uh like Friday and Saturday our
hours are extended in the evening till
about seven generally uh
about ten to five
in January and February
season because of us being in a kind of
a remote area there isn't a whole lot of
Tourism so generally we have in the past
always closed for those two months and I
probably perceived doing that again this
year especially in January because I'll
be in Lithuania for the last half of the
month so we probably won't be open
right but in March we opened back up to
a normal business hours and you're
hoping to have your pulse telegraphy
Studio up and running by late spring
early summer correct yep we're going in
January my laser engineer and I were
going uh
January and going back to see the folks
at geola and actually get the thing
wrapped up and hopefully we'll be there
uh first company in the United States to
actually have one of their jpxj systems
representative forum
[Music]
and hopefully
be able to be up and operational by
like I said late late time I mean early
summer
as our goal
any estimates on what it would cost to
have someone come through the door and
have a portrait done
at this point in time yeah we're we've
got a targeted price and this is kind of
a
a breakthrough here but we have a
targeted price of being able to do it
for uh
495 dollars to offer for one subject to
be recorded on a 12 by 16 inch glass
plate and they'll get a you know the
reflection copy on black
that's a considerably price reduction
over any holographic portraiture that's
been done in the past it's a pretty
neat thing to be able to offer it at
that price and we hope to really do well
at it um
now will you keep the master or will
they get the uh we would keep the master
but they would be able to get the white
light reflection copy and another thing
that keeps is that it would be a
same-day service the thing that's unique
about Jill is uh jpxj system is that you
can actually go from mastering the
copying mode with just a flick of a
switch and
okay I mean normally where you'd have oh
probably
four to eight man hours of
time involved in realigning Optics and
and going from
from the live stream to copying mode
that they've automated it to where it's
just actually a flick of a switch and
it's a matter of seconds that's great
a neat
involved in both photography because I
believe post photography is really the
wave of the future for uh display a lot
of things not only can you record
anything but it continuous Way
Photography setup can record but you can
also record
living objects
if you can actually
catch the shutter at the right time and
Trigger it right you can actually stop a
bullet in mid-air you know think of a
pulse
any final closing comments you'd like to
make for the whole talk listeners before
we close out
oh no that's why I thank you for uh
asking me
to go I know that I listen to your whole
talk show almost every week and your
website is a real valuable resource to
me too particularly your length page
your link page is just quite expensive
and photography related companies and
information and I use that real
frequently yeah that's that's all I have
left now
I I completely took the rest of the site
down all I have is going to be Hollow
talk on the link page now
because I think you know your next your
next Endeavor should be uh actually
publishing like a monthly
newsletter or uh design
I mean there's no resources for the
holography industry in general to be
able to look at besides uh Well
holography Marketplace and holography
news is about it anymore yeah especially
the art community the holographic
artists that they don't have a voice or
a medium to be heard on you know that
would be a neat thing to be able to do
is actually you know
like on a monthly
interval and you know have subscribers
on it what do you think
it could be I generally try to do that
with this show
and audio format where artists can come
on or people working with holography and
talk about their work did you catch the
uh last week's show with Steve Michael
where he's doing the Holograms with the
laser pointer
isn't that something I I didn't ever
think it was possible because
you hear about it not being possible so
no one ever tries it yeah someone like
that that ends up trying it because
Holograms are really nice I looked at
his website
um
events that he has displayed
there yeah all right God well thank you
very much for being on the show and good
luck for the holiday season coming on
and telling us what was hot and I'd like
to encourage the whole talk listeners to
go over to the fourth dimension
holographics website and check out what
they have over there
and talk to you again okay okay sounds
good sounds good thank you hold on a
second I'll pick up the phone after I uh
get the headphones and everything off
okay bye